A Guide to the "Smart" Road Citizen's Advisory Committee 1193-97
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
"Smart" Road Citizen's Advisory Committee 1993-97
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1997-025
0.6 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The "Smart" Road Citizen's Advisory Committee literature was donated by Dorothy Bodell of Blacksburg, Virginia, in 1997.
Biographical/Historical Information
The "Smart" Road is a project designed by the Virginia Department of Transportation to build a roadway as a direct link between Blacksburg and Roanoke, Virginia. The roadway was deemed necessary to alleviate congestion on the existing Route 460, particularly the portion that travels from Interstate 81 through Christiansburg to Blacksburg. The roadway would also serve as a test site for IVHS, or Intelligent Vehicle Highway Systems, "smart highway" technology. It was originally proposed that the roadway would be constructed as a four-lane facility on new alignments from I-81, approximately one mile north of its intersections with State Route 641, to the intersections of U.S. Business and Bypass Routes 460. The proposed highway would pass through the Ellett Valley of Montgomery County, Virginia.
In 1994 a citizen's advisory committee was formed to advise VDOT about the environmental and social ramifications of building the new roadway, as well as it's overall design. Issues the committee investigated included how an endangered species, the smooth coneflower, would be affected by the construction of the highway; the impact on the air quality of the Ellett Valley; impact on caves and karsts in the area; the destruction of cemeteries; and the flooding potential in the Roanoake River.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of reports, copies of electronic mail correspondence, brochures, meetings, minutes, and newspaper clippings about the "Smart" Road proposal. This information was collected by Dorothy Bodell of Blacksburg, Virginia, as she served on the citizen's advisory committee from January 1995 to July 1997.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.)
Contents List
- "Smart" Road Citizen's Advisory Committee 1993-97
  - Final Environment Impact Statement, Blacksburg/Roanoke Connector 1993 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Letter to Dorothy Bodell inviting her to join the "Smart" Road Committee December, 1994 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Phase 1 Cultural Resources Survey of the Two New Proposed Alignments for the "Smart" Highway December, 1994 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Pamplets on the "Smart" Road 1994-97 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - "Smart" - 060-Fol, Bike Trail Estimates March, 1995 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Meeting minutes March - November, 1995 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Project Schedule Status Screen May, 1995 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Property Owners Along Southern Alignment June, 1995 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - U.S. Department of the Interior, re: "Smart" Highway Biological Opinion July, 1995 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Resolutions of the Members of the Citizen's Advisory Committee for the "Smart" Road 1995 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Agricultural and Forestal Districts and the "Smart" Highway 1995-96 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Air Quality Analysis, Addendum to the Final Environmental Impact Statement, Fishburn Notes, Diagrams 1995-96 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Concerns of the Citizens Advisory Committee about the "Smart" Road 1995-96 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Newspaper clippings about the "Smart" Road 1995-96 (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Letters in Favor of the "Smart" Road 1995-96 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Miscellaneous literature 1995-96 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Email correspondence of the "Smart" Road Committee 1996 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Special Notice and Application Form for the Department of Transportation, "Smart" Road May, 1996 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Meeting minutes, information about "Smart" Road January - June, 1996 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Meeting minutes, Proposition for "Smart" Road July - October, 1996 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Meeting minutes January - July, 1997 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Environmental Reevaluation "Smart" Road April, 1997 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Photocopied article about "Smart" Road, Executive Summary of Response to VDOT, and Bodell's letter of resignation from the committee 1997 (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Information about the HKD Tower Snowgun n.d. (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Phone listings of members of the citizen's advisory committee n.d. (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Southern Alignment n.d. (Box-folder 2-8)